Guide to the John Judson Trappan Photographs 1888–1912, undated PR 071
New-York Historical Society
John Judson Trappan photographs
1888–1912, undated
New-York Historical Society
Trappan, John Judson, 1867-1957
PR 071
10.3 Linear feet in 15 boxes.
A record of the travels of bicycling and photography enthusiast John Judson Trappan (1867–1957), a Brooklyn, New York native whose trips took him to Long Island, upstate New York, Connecticut, and Massachusetts, during the late 19th and early 20th centuries. More distant visits found Trappan in Chicago for the World's Columbian Exposition (1893), in Buffalo for the Pan-American Exposition (1901), in Washington, D.C. for the inauguration of Theodore Roosevelt (1901), and in Philadelphia and Washington, D.C. for his honeymoon (1903), all of which are documented by photographs in the collection. Other scenes depict his family in Brooklyn, a church dinner, local outings, landmarks in various cities, and some of Trappan's coworkers at Bruce & Cook, the Manhattan sheet metal firm where he was employed as a bookkeeper. Formats include 10 albums (containing 462 photographic prints), circa 290 loose and mounted prints, and 659 negatives (385 glass, mostly 4 x 5 inches, and 274 film). The collection is supplemented by the photographer's logbook, two handwritten journals, a few postcards, souvenir view books, clippings, bicycling ephemera, travel brochures, a painted canvas book cover, and material from Bruce & Cook.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in three series:
Series I.
Photographs, 1888–1909, undated
Series II.
Negatives, 1890–1903, undated
Series III.
Ephemera, 1888–1912, undated
Biographical note
John Judson Trappan was born in 1867 in Williamsburg, Brooklyn, to John J. Trappan, a gasfitter, and Susanna Park. As a young man he was interested in boating and bicycling, and actively pursued both pastimes. Trappan took many bicycle trips, which often involved overnight camping. He journeyed, mainly by bicycle, to Connecticut, upstate New York, Massachusetts, and Washington, D.C., to attend religious conventions, see World's Fairs and presidential inaugurations, and to enjoy natural wonders and the company of his friends. He spent summers boating off the coasts of Queens and Long Island, and was active in the Tompkins Avenue Congregational Church.
Trappan was employed as a bookkeeper for the firm of Bruce & Cook, located on Water Street in Manhattan. After his father's death, John continued to live with his mother and two younger sisters, Ella and Caroline, and supported the family. Ella and Carrie both worked as schoolteachers, and accompanied John on many of his boating adventures.
John Judson Trappan married Ada in 1903, and they moved to Ridgewood, New Jersey, where they raised four daughters: Ruth (1904–1997), Grace (1905–1998), Jean (1907–1998), and Elizabeth (1909–1996). Trappan died in 1957.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers by appointment only. To schedule an appointment, contact the Print Room Librarian at printroom@nyhistory.org.
Due to the possible combustibility of the nitrate negatives in Subseries II.D, that portion of the collection (Box 13) is kept in cold storage. Before requesting it, discuss the possibility of viewing this material with a staff member, keeping in mind that it requires at least two full days to thaw.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Ruth Trappan, 1984.
Related Materials
Other photographs of 19th century bicyclists can be found in the Subject File (PR 068) and the Geographic Images Collection (PR 020).
Ruth Trappan, donor of the present collection, also gave the New-York Historical Society a significant portion of material in the Robert L. Bracklow Photograph Collection (PR 008).
Scope and Contents
The collection spans the period 1888–1912 and documents John Judson Trappan's interest in two popular turn-of-the-20th century American pastimes: bicycling and photography.
Series I. Photographs, 1888–1909, undated is divided in two subseries: Photographic Albums and Loose Photographs. Subseries I.A contains ten travel albums created by Trappan from photographs taken during trips and bicycle journeys in New York, New England, and Montreal, Canada. Two handwritten travel journals that correspond with the trips shown in the albums "A Coastwise Trip Awheel" and "Berkshire Hills Trip" are housed with those albums. In addition to photos, the albums also contain personal materials such as pressed flowers, poems, bars of music, and quotations. The eight titled albums are all arranged in bound, probably store-bought, album covers. Most of these are paper covers, but a few have more substantial vinyl or leather covers.
The albums are arranged chronologically, with undated albums filed at the end. "Haps and Snaps," taken in 1892 at Morris Cove, Connecticut, is comprised of 3x5-inch cyanotypes. "Bits of Scattered Sunshine" documents a trip Trappan took to Massachusetts in 1895 to attend the 14th International Christian Endeavor Convention at Mechanics Hall in Boston. One photo shows the interior of the hall filled with conventioneers. During this trip Trappan also photographed tourist sites in Boston as well as those in Concord, Lexington, Marblehead, Salem, and Northfield. Photos of the homes of Ralph Waldo Emerson, Louisa May Alcott, and Nathaniel Hawthorne are paired with quotations from those authors. Images of Morris Cove and New Haven, Connecticut are also included.
An album titled "Berkshire Hills" contains photographs taken on a bicycling trip in which Trappan and his friend Edward Oberholser took the Hudson River Day Line up the Hudson to Poughkeepsie, and cycled from there to the Berkshire Hills in western Massachusetts. The accompanying travel journal, which is undated, but was written after the trip, includes some humorous anecdotes of the men's' visit to Vassar College. "A Coastwise Trip Awheel" contains cyanotypes of a bicycling trip Trappan made with his friend George Ellison to Connecticut via Long Island and a ferry between the northern coast of Long Island and New London. This album is also accompanied by a manuscript journal, and two envelopes of loose cyanotypes from the trip.
"Inauguration," includes photos taken at the 1901 presidential inauguration of Theodore Roosevelt. It is unclear if Trappan bicycled to Washington, D.C. Crowds and decorated buildings in Washington are highlighted. "Pan American Exposition" documents Trappan's trip to the Buffalo world's fair in June 1901. Many of these photographs are night views fair's hallmark displays of electricity. Daytime photos show the Exposition buildings and Midway amusements. Trappan seems to have done a combination of bicycling and train plus boat travel on this voyage. On the way to Buffalo he visited and photographed Watkins Glen, Genesee Falls, the Minnehaha Falls, and the Erie Canal. After visiting the Fair he continued to Niagara Falls and then to Montreal. There are several cyanotypes in this album.
"Wedding Trip" is a document of Trappan's honeymoon in 1903. Trappan and his wife traveled to Philadelphia, Hampton, Williamsburg, Jamestown, and Richmond, Virginia, and Washington, D.C.
Two untitled groups of photographs seem to have been bound into makeshift albums by Trappan himself. One contains photographs mounted onto board that is then bound together with string. These photographs show an unidentified river and waterfall. Stanzas from a poem about a brook are interspersed with the photographs. The other untitled album is made up of cyanotypes clipped together at the upper left edges. They show a group of men bicycling and camping together in an unidentified locale.
Also included in this subseries are photographs mounted together on display boards; most are duplicate prints from the photo albums.
Subseries I.B. Loose Photographs, spans the years 1890–1893 and includes images of Connecticut, Illinois, Massachusetts, New York, and Virginia. These seem to have been taken during Trappan's travels, but in general are not duplicates of photographs found in the albums. Loose photographs are arranged geographically and then by subject. Most of these photographs are mounted on card. A group of cyanotypes of the World's Columbian Exposition in Chicago in 1893 are included in this subseries. New York images include views of Central Park (including the zoo), Flushing (a cyanotype of bicyclists there), and sailboats off College Point in Flushing Bay. Views of Brooklyn include images of Coney Island, Sunday School parades, and several views of cyclists in Prospect Park. Unidentified portraits include more groups of bicyclists, and people in classrooms and at picnics. Several photos show congregants of the Tompkins Avenue Congregational Church dressed up for a "New England" dinner.
Series II. Negatives, 1890–1903, undated is organized in four subseries: Logbook, Glass Plate Negatives (4 x 5"), Glass Plate Negatives (5 x 8"), and Nitrate Film Negatives. The logbook (1890–1901) consists of photocopies of twenty handwritten pages that provide such details as negative number, date, subject, location, time of day, light, exposure, F-stop, plate size, plate maker, plate style, photographer, and remarks. The logbook corresponds to the glass negatives. All the negatives listed in the logbook do not appear in the collection. A list of negatives, with titles taken from the logbook, appears in the box and folder list. Within the series, unnumbered negatives are arranged by subject, while numbered negatives are arranged numerically. No attempt was made during processing to match prints to negatives. Due to the possible combustibility of the nitrate negatives in Subseries II.D, that portion of the collection (Box 13) is kept in cold storage. Before requesting it, discuss the possibility of viewing this material with a staff member, keeping in mind that it requires at least two full days to thaw.
Series III. Ephemera, 1888–1912, undated includes material collected by Trappan relating to his interests. Photographic ephemera includes a copy of the July 20, 1888 issue of Photographic Times. Bicycling material includes two of Trappan's American Wheelmen Association membership cards and an 1897 catalog for Keating Bicycles. Included are several souvenir post cards, travel brochures, and a souvenir booklet from the 1893 Chicago World's Fair. Material from the steel-working firm Bruce & Cook includes photographs of the firm (see Series II for a few negatives showing the basement of their Water Street office), the centennial celebration dinner (1912) program, and business cards. Also included in this series are two hand-painted covers for a book and photo portfolio.
Cyanotypes.; Gelatin silver prints.; negatives (photographs); Photographic prints.; Portraits.; Travel photography.; Bicycle touring -- Massachusetts.; Bicycle touring -- New York (State) -- Long Island.; Church dinners -- New York (State) -- New York.; Cycling.; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Photographs.; Long Island (N.Y.) -- Photographs.; Massachusetts -- Photographs.; New York (State) -- Photographs.; Philadelphia (Pa.) -- Photographs.; Washington (D.C.) -- Photographs.; Trappan (Family); Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919 -- Inauguration -- Photographs; Bruce & Cook; Keating Wheel Company; Pan-American Exposition [611] (1901: Buffalo, N.Y.) -- Photographs; World's Columbian Exposition (1893: Chicago, Ill.) [111] -- Photographs
- Series I. Photographs, 1888–1909, undated
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged in two subseries: I.A. Photograph Albums, and I.B. Loose Photographs.
  - Subseries I.A. Photograph Albums, 1892–1903, undated
    Albums are arranged chronologically.
    - "Haps and Snaps, Morris Cove, Conn.", 1892 July (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    - "Bits of Scattered Sunshine", 1895 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    - "Berkshire Hills" (includes manuscript account of the trip), 1898 October 10–15 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
    - "A Coastwise Trip Awheel" (includes manuscript account of the trip), 1900 July 16 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Inauguration March 4th 1901", 1901 March 4 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Pan American Exposition", 1901 June (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - "Wedding Trip", 1903 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
    - Untitled [river and waterfall], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
    - Untitled [bicycling and camping trip], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
    - Mounted Photographs (24 boards), 1897–1899 (Offsite-box 2)
  - Subseries I.B. Loose Photographs, 1888–1909, undated
    Photographs are arranged geographically and then by subject.
    - Connecticut—East Haven, 1891 July (Offsite-box 3, Folder 10)
    - Connecticut—Morris Cove, 1890–1891 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 11)
    - Connecticut—Newtown, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 12)
    - Illinois—Chicago—World's Columbian Exposition, 1893 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 13)
    - Massachusetts—New Bedford, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 14)
    - Massachusetts—North Adams, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 14)
    - New York—Binghamton, 1890 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 15)
    - New York—Little Neck Bay (Long Island), 1891 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 16)
    - New York City—Brooklyn—General, 1890, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 17)
    - New York City—Brooklyn—Prospect Park, 1890, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 18)
    - New York City—Manhattan—General, 1890–1891, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 19)
    - New York City—Manhattan—Central Park, 1891 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 20)
    - New York City—Queens—College Point/Flushing Bay, 1891 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 21)
    - New York City—Queens—Flushing, 1891 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 22)
    - New York—Nanuet, 1891 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 23)
    - New York—Pelham Bay, 1893 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 24)
    - New York—Rockland County, 1892 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 25)
    - New York—Shady Glen, 1894 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 26)
    - New York—Union, 1892, 1909 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 27)
    - Pennsylvania—Mt. Jefferson, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 28)
    - Virginia—Mt. Vernon, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 29)
    - Unidentified locations—Outdoor views, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 30)
    - Unidentified locations—Portrait photographs, 1891–1892, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 31)
    - Unidentified locations—Residences, 1892, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 32)
    - Unidentified locations—Sailboats, 1888, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 33)
- Series II. Negatives, 1890–1903, undated
  Series II is organized in four subseries: II.A. Logbook; II.B. Glass Plate Negatives (4 x 5"); II.C. Glass Plate Negatives (5 x 8"); and II.D. Nitrate Film Negatives.
  - Subseries II.A. Logbook, 1890–1901
    - Logbook (photocopies), 1890–1901 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 34)
  - Subseries II.B. Glass Plate Negatives (4 x 5"), 1890–1901, undated
    Numbered glass plate negatives are housed sequentially from 007 to 494; there are gaps in the series. The negatives correspond to the entries in the photographer's logbook (Subseries II.A). Unnumbered negatives follow the numbered negatives, and have been arranged by subject. The quantity of negatives in each subject grouping is listed in parentheses.
    - Glass Plate Negatives (4 x 5")—numbered [part 1 of 5], 1890–1893 (Box 6)
      Scope and Contents
      007—Group of office force, 1890 February 14
      019—Group – School marms, PS #53, 1890 April 3
      021—E. L. Tibbulo, 1890 April 10
      027a—Group, Missus Schmidt, Miller & Carrie, PS #53, 1890 May 9
      030—New Iron Bridge, Prospect Park, 1890 May 17
      036—Moore's Bust, Prospect Park, 1890 May 24
      041—Rear of Houses, Morris Cove, 1890 July 14
      049—Houses, front view, Binghamton, 1890 July 23
      066—Barge Office, Battery Park, 1890 June 1
      068a—In the hands of friends (?), Battery Park, 1890 June 1
      068b—In the hands of friends (?), Battery Park, 1890 June 1
      069—Chas. Stout, 190 Water St., 1890 June 10
      070—American Bison, Central Park, 1891 February 19
      072—Carrie, Parlor, 1890 July 4
      073—Ella, Parlor, 1890 July 4
      074—Sailing party, Morris Cove, 1891 July 29
      074?—
      075—Hay Riders, New Light House, 1891 July 30
      076—Light House, South End, 1891 July 30
      077—Lunch party, South End, 1891 July 30
      078—E. Haven Cong. Ch., E. Haven, 1891 July 31
      079—Lake Saltonstall, E. Haven, 1891 July 31
      082—Lotta Spoerl + Auntie, Nanuet, 1891 September 4
      083b—Group, Spring Valley, 1891 September 7
      084—Lotta Fishing, Nanuet, 1891 September 4
      087—In the woods, muddy brook—Nanuet, 1891 September 4
      088—Eagle cage, Central Park, 1891 October 24
      089—Reservoir House, Central Park, 1891 October 24
      093a—Edward Lester Tibbols, Central Park, 1891
      093b—
      104—Fulton Fish Market, 1891 July
      106—Kitty, 1892 August
      108—Rob & horse, Morris Cove, 1892 July
      109—Group in orchard, Morris Cove, 1892 July
      110—Lulu & horse, front of house, Morris Cove, 1892 July
      110a—
      112—At the picnic, Cranford Point, 1892 July
      113—Columbus Celebration, City Hall, N.Y., 1892 October
      114—Columbus Celebration, Post Office, N.Y., 1892 October
      115—Columbus Celebration, Lower B'way, N.Y., 1892 October
      116—Columbus Celebration, Wall St., N.Y., 1892 October
      117—Columbus Celebration, Naval Parade, N.Y., 1892 October
      117—
      118—Columbus Celebration, N.Y., 1892 October
      119—Columbus Celebration, West St., roof gazers, N.Y., 1892 October
      120—Rob's café & picnic group, E. Haven & Branford, Conn., 1892 July
      121—Sailor girls, Morris Cove, 1892 July
      122—Farmer Robt has cow, Morris Cove, 1892 July
      123—Cows under tree, E. Haven, 1892 July
      124—Dou and his rider, Morris Cove, 1892 July
      128—Decoration Day, Pelham Bay, summerhouse, 1893 May 30
      129—Decoration Day, Pelham Bay, the Gus, 1893 May 30
      131—Po'keepsie Bridge from Albany dayboat, 1893 July 10
      132—Niagara Rapids from Prospect Park gate, 1893 July 10
      133—Falls from above inclined RR, 1893 July 10
      134—Falls from "Maid of Mist" station, 1893 July 10
      135—Girls on deck of "Maid of Mist," 1893 July 10
      136—Horseshoe Falls from "Maid of Mist," 1893 July 10
      136?—
      137—Whirlpool, 1893 July 10
      141—Ferris wheel and bicyclist, 1893 July 18
      142—Ferris wheel and group, 1893 July 18
      143—Group in Washington Park, 1893 July 18
      144—"Sol's clock" in Washington Park, 1893 July 18
      145—Gates ajar in Washington Park, 1893 July 18
      146—Looking north from Transportation Building, 1893 July 20
      147—From bridge in front of Transportation Building, 1893 July 20
      148—Machinery Hall & McMonnies fountain, 1893 July 20
      149—Colonnade from bridge in court of Honor, 1893 July 20
      151—Statue in Court of Honor "the Producer," 1893 July 20
      152—Administration Bldg from Peristyle, 1893 July 20
      153—Statue of Republic, 1893 July 20
    - Glass Plate Negatives (4 x 5")—numbered [part 2 of 5], 1893–1895 (Box 7)
      156—McMonnies fountain & Mining Bldg., 1893 July 20
      157—In Midway going west, 1893 July 20
      158—Lunch party on Mich. Piazza, 1893 July 20
      159—57th St. entrance—looking east, 1893 July 20
      161—Spectatorium—from N.Y. bldg. Tower, 1893 July 20
      162—Looking south—from N.Y. bldg. Tower, 1893 July 20
      163—Viking ship & U.S.S. "Illinois," 1893 July 20
      164—From bridge looking toward colonnade, 1893 July 20
      165—Front of Trans. Bldg. & chair, 1893 July 20
      166—Admin. Bldg., 1893 July 20
      167—Guards, 1893 July 20
      168—From west end of Court of Honor, 1893 July 20
      169—Gondolas & bridge south of "Lib. Arts," 1893 July 20
      170—Gondolas (side view), 1893 July 20
      172—Group – eating at Mill Creek, Aurora, Illinois, 1893 July 24
      173—Group on stump at Mill Creek, Aurora, Illinois, 1893 July 24
      174—Group on stoop at Mill Creek, Aurora, Illinois, 1893 July 26
      175—E. H. Brooks house, Aurora, Illinois, 1893 July 26
      176—Stage party, Aurora, Illinois, 1893 July 24
      179—Bennett family, Kalamazoo, 1893 August
      180—Watson House, Crooked Lake, 1893 August
      181—Bennett cottage, Crooked Lake, 1893 August
      182—Group at lunch, Crooked Lake, 1893 August
      183—Boats on lake, Crooked Lake, 1893 August
      184—Water Lilies, Crooked Lake, 1893 August
      185—Grimmell Family, Cleveland, 1893 August
      195—Bronx Park Dam, 1894 May 30
      197—At Lunch, Little Neck Bay, 1894 July 4
      198—Making Coffee, Little Neck Bay, 1894 July 4
      199—Mrs. Cooper, Little Neck Bay, 1894 July 4
      200—Douglaston Boat Club House, 1894 July 4
      201—In the boat, Little Neck Bay, 1894 July 4
      203—Tredwells House, Sheepshead Bay, 1894 Aug 4
      204—Tredwells House, Sheepshead Bay, some moved, 1894 Aug 4
      205—Tredwells Yacht, 1894 August 4
      206—New England Dinner Party, Tomp. Ave. Church, 1894 November 28
      219—The "Fly" on starboard tack, Jamaica Bay, 1894 August-September
      220—The "Fly" at breakwater, Jamaica Bay, 1894 August-September
      227—Ferry over Conn. River, Northfield to Mt. Hermon, 1895 July 6
      228—Group at Mr. Alford's—Bernardston, 1895 July 6
      229—Group at Mr. Alford's—Bernardston, 1895 July 6
      230—Girls at Mr. Alford's—Bernardston, 1895 July 6
      231—Sow and pigs, Northfield, 1895 July 8
      232—Wanamaker Lake falls, 1895 July 8
      233—Wanamaker Lake above falls, J & dog, 1895 July 8
      234—Moody cottage, D.L.M. born here, 1895 July 8
      235—Our tent 1895, July 8
      236—Our tent—fishing, firing, etc., 1895 July 8
      237—Group at tents—bicycles, 1895 July 8
      238—Group at tents—bicycles grotesque, 1895 July 8
      239—Group at tents—two tents, 1895 July 8
      240—Group at tents—two tents, boys painting, 1895 July 8
      241—Hotel de barn—John Lotz—caterer, 1895 July 10
      242—Harvard statue—Cambridge, 1895 July 11
      243—Soldiers monument on green—Cambridge, 1895 July 11
      244—Washington Elm, 1895 July 11
      245—Mechanics Hall—end view, 1895 July 12
      246—Mechanics Hall—entrance, 1895 July 12
      247—Mechanics Hall—interior, 1895 July 12
      248—Faneuil Hall, 1895 July 12
      249—Old book store, 1895 July 12
      250—Old State House, 1895 July 12
      251—Old North Church or Christ Church, 1895 July 12
      252—Trinity Church, 1895 July 13
      253—Decorations on Washington Street, 1895 July 13
      254—Bridge in Public Gardens, 1895 July 15
      255—C. E. Tents, 1895 July 15
    - Glass Plate Negatives (4 x 5")—numbered [part 3 of 5], 1895–1896 (Box 8)
      256—Soldiers Monument on Common, 1895 July 15
      257—State House, 1895 July 15
      258—Congregational House, 1895 July 15
      259—Emerson's House, Concord, 1895 July 15
      260—Alcott House, Concord, 1895 July 15
      261—Hawthorne House, Concord, 1895 July 15
      262—Hosmer House, Concord, 1895 July 15
      263—Emerson's grave, Sleepy Hollow, 1895 July 15
      264—Old Manse, 1895 July 15
      265—Old No. Bridge & Monument, 1895 July 15
      266—Statue of Minute Man, 1895 July 15
      267—Wright Tavern, 1895 July 15
      269—Dog & child, 1895 July 15
      270—Clark House (Hancock & Adams), 1895 July 15
      272—Monument, Plymouth, 1895 July 16
      273—Monument, Plymouth, 1895 July 16
      274—Judson's grave, 1895 July 16
      275—Plymouth Rock, 1895 July 16
      276—The churn, Marblehead Neck, 1895 July 17
      277—Castle Rock, Marblehead Neck, 1895 July 17
      278—Rocks and breakers, Marblehead Neck, 1895 July 17
      279—Rocks and breakers, Marblehead Neck, 1895 July 17
      280—Tucker House, Marblehead, 1895 July 17
      281—Lee Mansion, Marblehead, 1895 July 17
      283—Custom House, Salem, 1895 July 17
      284—McCleve House, 1895 July-August
      285—McCleve Cottage, 1895 July-August
      286—Morris House, 1895 July-August